<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from a member of the parliament of Scotland to his friend at London, concerning their late act, for establishing a company of that kingdom, tradeing to Africa and the Indies</title>
            <author>Verax, Philanax.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87931</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1413</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231897</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897507</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897507</idno>
            <idno type="VID">137279</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87931)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 137279)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2502:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from a member of the parliament of Scotland to his friend at London, concerning their late act, for establishing a company of that kingdom, tradeing to Africa and the Indies</title>
                  <author>Verax, Philanax.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at London, and re-printed at Edinburgh, by the heirs and successors of Andrew Anderson, printer to the King's most excellent Majesty,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[Edinburgh] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Philonax Verax.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the John Carter Brown Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Company of Scotland Trading to Africa and the Indies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland. --  Act for a company trading to Africa and the Indies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Trading companies --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Trading companies --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:137279:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:137279:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER From a MEMBER of the Parliament of Scotland To his Friend at LONDON, <hi>Concerning their late ACT, for Eſtabliſhing a Company of that Kingdom, Tradeing to</hi> Africa <hi>and the</hi> Indies.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>—</hi> Ridentem dicere verum,</l>
               <l>Quid vetat?<hi>—Horat.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Contraria Juxta ſe poſita clarius cluceſcunt.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Account you give me by your laſt, of the various Shapes into which ſome Perſons at <hi>London</hi> have tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed our late Act of Parliament, for Eſtabliſhing a <hi>Company Tradeing to</hi> Africa <hi>and the</hi> Indies, and their repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it under ſo many ſeveral Colours, to thoſe of different Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities and Affections, puts me in mind of the Shepherd, who, ambitious to be thought Weather-wiſe never fail'd with an air of Gravity, to publiſh his pretended Revelations of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:137279:2"/>enſuing Weather, in various and quite contrary manners to his ſeveral Proſelites, thereby ſecuring to himſelf certain Eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in all Weathers that could happen, if any ſhould dare to call the Infallibility of his Predictions into queſtion. And re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, The exact Idea you give me of the manner in which theſe Perſons ſeem to buſie themſelves in other Mens Affairs, affords me matter ſufficient to renew my Speculation, concerning the precarious Nature of all Mankind, in point of Intereſt; and by Retroſpection into ſome Tranſactions of this and the laſt Age, I am induced to trouble you with the following Narrative of ſome Obſervations naturally ariſing from the ſame, which to me ſeem directly to point at the Temper, Inclination, and real Intereſt of all <hi>BRITAIN:</hi> But before I launch into ſo wide an Ocean; I cannot forbear expreſſing the Satisfaction I have in reflecting, That the whole Repreſentatives of a Nation ſo little experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in Trade, as ours, ſhould with ſo unanimous a Voice <hi>(Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine contradicente)</hi> agree to ſuch Meaſures and Foundation of Trade, as now ſeem worth the Notice of ſo great a People as our Neighbouring Nation; and my Satisfaction therein is ſtill the more exalted, by finding in your Account, That the moſt Sober and Tradeing People of that Kingdom, are ſo far from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving any diſguſt at, or diſlike to it, that they generally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs an Inclination to be concerned in it: Excepting (as you obſerve) a few who (every body knows) are preingaged to a dear Self-monopoliſing Intereſt, together with ſome few others, whoſe Inſtructions from a Forreign Court muſt in all probability oblige them to lay hold of any ſeeming Opportunity for blowing the Coal of Sedition in this Iſland, that they may Fiſh in troubled Waters: And as a little Leaven leaveneth the whole Lump, you muſt always expect to find ſuch Perſons very vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, by their Emiſſaries, to amuſe the Unthinking Crowd with groundleſs Apparitions; and by a more induſtrious Artifice, have their deſigning Inſinuations buz'd into the Ears of ſome great Miniſters, who having the bent of their Thoughts employed
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:137279:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>about Matters of State and Government, ſutable to the great Sphere in which they move, may poſſibly, through want of Time, conſider this Matter no further than by a bare ſuperficial View of ſuch fallacious Poſitions as may probably, by Prepoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion be dogmatically obtruded upon them, to ſerve private Ends, though mask'd under the ſpecious Pretences of a National Concern. Wherefore, I hope thoſe worthy Gentlemen at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> who are concerned in this Company, will endeavour to anticipate any evil Effect of theſe or the like Miſ-repreſentations and groundleſs Suggeſtions mention'd in your Letter, by ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viating the Fallacy of ſuch noiſie Arguments as (you ſay) are daily with an Ayre of Magiſterial Stiffneſs dictated at <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raways,</hi> and from thence diffus'd amongſt the credulous Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude; which, whenſoever impartially examin'd and conſider'd, will doubtleſs appear to have no other Merit at bottom, than a Nooſe of Sophiſtry to catch Woodcocks in. For there was never any Conſtitution of Trade concerted by any free King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, State or Common-wealth in <hi>Europe,</hi> with greater regard to the Conſtitutions and Priviledges of all other Nations in Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with His Majeſty, than this hath been: yea, ſhould we have had a Committee of Engliſh Merchants to Examine and Report our Proceedings while we were paſſing this ACT, they could not poſſibly have been more nicely tender of Encroaching upon, or Interferring with the Engliſh Immunities, either Abroad or at home, than we have been. And in regard that Pyracy, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtility, and all manner of violent Force, is not only inconſiſtent with, but diametrically oppoſite to the natural Laws and Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of Trade, we have, in the Body of this ACT, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded the <hi>Company</hi> from Acting or Settling in the very <hi>Indies,</hi> without Conſent of the Natives. And, in ſhort, we had then the Law of Nations ſo immediately under our Conſideration, that it was thought by the moſt Precautious of our Aſſembly, we had left no room for ſo much as a poſſibility of Cavilling. But there's none ſo blind as they who will not ſee; and by what
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:137279:3"/>you write, I find, had there been any thing in our <hi>Act</hi> that could not bear the Trial of the ſtricteſt Enquiry on the aforeſaid Heads, it had certainly been long e're now ript up and printed in Capital Letters by thoſe who were at the Trouble and Expence of Re-printing the Act at <hi>London</hi> in ſeveral ſhapes, and under a new Title of their own framing, of deſign to adapt it more properly to the Notion of Rivalſhip and Emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which (you ſay) they ſo induſtriouſly preach in Coffee-houſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> O! but (ſay they,) Tho' there be nothing in the <hi>Act</hi> that at preſent may ſeem to interferr with, yet in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence it may prove pernicious to the Intereſt of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Anſwer to which, give me leave to obſerve, That as this <hi>Act</hi> was calculated for a Common and Publick Good, ſo though it be a received and ſtanding Maxim, That <hi>No Evil is to be done, that Good may come of it;</hi> yet no reaſonable Man will urge from thence the Alternative, <hi>That we ought to forbear doing an apparent Publick Good, becauſe of a remote poſſibility of an imaginary Evil Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And before <hi>I</hi> ſtep further, pray let us take a ſhort View of what Proſpect there may be of this bug bearing Conſequence. Why, truly <hi>Scotland</hi> propoſeth an Advantage by Foreign Trade, &amp; leaves it at <hi>England</hi>'s door to accept or refuſe, being concerned for one Moie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of all the Profits, Emoluments &amp; Advantages ariſing from ſuch Trade; &amp; by the bye <hi>England</hi>'s embracing that Offer, ſeems to me an auſpicious Prognoſtick of future Succeſs Now, ſhould we happen to be fruſtrate in our Expectation by this Trade, then all the vain Jealouſies of Rivalſhip &amp; Competition fall of courſe. But if it ſhould (as <hi>I</hi> hope it may) anſwer our Wiſhes, by a plentiful &amp; proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Harveſt, in return to our Honeſt and Infant Undertaking, <hi>England,</hi> ſure, would be mightily hurt, to reap One Half of all
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:137279:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Profits thereof; which I pray God may prove the happy Conſequence, ſo much ſear'd by your Monopoly-men.</p>
            <p>Yet all this (you ſay) cannot pleaſe them that are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to be implacable, for that there are a certain ſort of ſuch good-natur'd Chriſtians in the World, as would chuſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to loſe a certain Benefit and Advantage to themſelves, than endure the very thoughts of ſeeing their Neighbours in any tolerable degree of equal Proſperity. In alluſion to which, 'tis no new thing to tell you, That ever ſince the Reformation of Religion, the Jeſuits, in their various ſhapes, have left no means uneſſayed, to propagate the ſeveral Sects and Schiſms which, during the laſt Age, have, like a general Contagion, overſpread this Iſland, and undoubtedly gave the firſt riſe to all the ſad Cataſtrophe and diſmal Conſequences of the late bloody Civil Wars. And even ſo, ſince the Union of both Kingdoms under one Monarchy, we have too too manifeſt and pregnant Proof of how far the <hi>Matchevilian</hi> Maxims of Policy have, by the means of <hi>French</hi> Penſioners and Emiſſaries, gain'd credit enough at the Court of <hi>England,</hi> to improve the Remnants and Dregs of the ancient Feuds of both Kingdons into an almoſt avowed Reaſon of State (though a much miſtaken one) <hi>That it was the Intereſt of</hi> England, <hi>to ſuppreſs and keep</hi> Scotland <hi>poor.</hi> Which was indeed chiefly intended, and contrived with deſign to leave <hi>England</hi> in the lurch, and carry on the real Intereſt of <hi>France,</hi> where this Maxim had its birth, by re-gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Scotland</hi> into their ancient League.</p>
            <p>For the Sting and hidden Poyſon of the Serpent lay in this, That the People of <hi>Scotland,</hi> from the natural conſideration they muſt needs have of any ſevere Treatment, or unreaſonable and intolerable Exactions impoſed upon them by their domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neering Neighbours, might in time be tempted, like the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the Wilderneſs, to <hi>murmur</hi> and <hi>look back into the Onions, Melons, Garlick, and Fleſh-pots of their old acquaintance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet by the Influence of this Jeſuitical, Barbarous and Helliſh
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:137279:4"/>Principle, together with the general Corruption of ſuch collea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing and ſelf-deſigning Miniſters as have (to the grief of theſe Nations) been at the Helm of Affairs during thoſe latter Reigns, this poor Nation in particular hath been moſt unmercifully crampt and fetter'd in its natural Liberties, both as to Religion, Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Trade, and indeed, all the real Badges of a Free and inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent Kingdom, other than in ſhadow; till the late Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dential and Happy Revolution gave us not only a fair opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of reaſſuming all our ancient Freedoms, and natural Liberties, but alſo of extending the ſame, in point of Trade, far beyond thoſe Limits which ſome of our Neighbours ſeem now unwilling to allow us.</p>
            <p>And <hi>I</hi> would gladly offer it to the ſerious Conſideration of any Honeſt, Unbyaſs'd and Free-thinking <hi>Engliſh-man,</hi> Whether, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon His preſent Majeſty's Acceſſion to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> when <hi>Ireland</hi> was in a manner quite lopp'd off, <hi>France</hi> making mighty Preparations for War, all <hi>Europe</hi> invelop'd in almoſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable Flames; and <hi>England</hi> it ſelf, not free from Inteſtine Diviſions, and Boſom Enemies, who flattered themſelves with the Hopes that <hi>Scotland</hi> would, from the conſideration of its being ſo long kept at Arm's length, be tempted to act by an Intereſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from that of <hi>England?</hi> Whether (<hi>I</hi> ſay) upon condition of aſſurance then, that we would follow <hi>England</hi>'s Example, in placing the Crown of this Realm upon the Heads of our preſent Gracious Soveraign, and His late Royal Confort (of Bleſſed Memory) when they fear'd our Demurring upon it, <hi>England</hi> would not have willingly fulfilled, and put us in poſſeſſion of the long promiſed Union of both Nations; and ſettled the ſame upon ſuch an equal and laſting Foundation, as that we might have freedom of Trading into the very Heart of their Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions?</p>
            <p>For, how little ſoever the apparent Proportion be, which our Nation may at preſent ſeem to bear on the Theatre of Publick
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:137279:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>Action, as being in a manner wholly eclipſed by the refulgent and radiant Beams of <hi>England</hi>'s more reſplendent Greatneſs, <hi>I</hi> may without Hyperbole juſtly ſay, That as Matters then ſtood, We had the Ballance of <hi>Europe</hi> in our Hands.</p>
            <p>Yet all the Conſiderations we had in view of our own particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Intereſt, &amp; the Advantages which we might have made of that Opportunity, ſoon gave way to the irreſiſtable Zeal and Affection which we had for the reſtorer of the Proteſtant Religion, and common Liberties of <hi>Britain.</hi> For leſt that by any Delays in our Proceedings, the Meaſures of <hi>England</hi> might be protracted, We did, in almoſt One Breath, Declare the Throne Vacant, our Selves a Free, Independent State. Their Royal Highneſſes King and Queen of this Realm, and war againſt all Their Majeſty's E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies; as not in the leaſt doubting, but that ſuch our generous and frank Proceeding, with reſpect to our Neighbours, at ſo critical a Juncture of Affairs, might in due time reaſonably plead for a grateful Reſentment from the King and Parliament of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> by an equally generous Condeſcenſion, on their ſide, to our having the ſame freedom of Trade, by which, but a little time before, the wiſeſt and moſt leading Men of that Nation thought it their Intereſt to have ſecured our Affection.</p>
            <p>And that this was the ſenſe of the Court of <hi>England</hi> at that time, needs no further evidence than His Majeſty's two ſucceſſive <hi>Speeches</hi> to both Houſes of His Firſt Parliament; wherein the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of an intire Union with <hi>Scotland</hi> was ſeriouſly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended: In order to which, ſome Schemes were prepared and conſulted by certain Noble Patriots of both Nations.</p>
            <p>But no ſooner had we in the interim, ſolemnly conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated, in manner aforeſaid, all that <hi>England</hi> could have either wiſh'd or fear'd from us on that Occaſion; but of a ſudden all thoughts of ſuch Union fell to the ground: ſo that being left
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:137279:5"/>to chew our Cud upon that melancholly Proverb, <hi>Poſt eſt occaſio calva,</hi> which in our Dialect may be render'd, <hi>A True Scotch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is Wiſe behind-hand;</hi> our next and only Remedy was, to <hi>make the beſt of a bad Mercat.</hi> In order to which, we then Reſoved to think of framing ſuch wholſom and advantagious Laws for the Advancement of our poor Trade, as might not only rouze up and animat the depreſſed and often-diſappointed Genius of our fellow-Natives, but alſo invite and enduce Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers more experienced in Trade, to embarque upon the ſame bottom with us: and to that end, We did, in the Third Seſſion of this current Parliament, <hi>Anno</hi> 1693. Paſs a Prelimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary <hi>Act,</hi> conceived in general Terms, <hi>for the Encouragement of Foreign Trade,</hi> which you ſee narrated in the beginning of this laſt <hi>Act:</hi> By the gracious and neceſſary Conceſſions of which, we have a plain Demonſtration, through the Vertue of thoſe Noble and worthy Patriots whom His Majeſty's diſcerning Eye ſingled out of the Crowd of Pretenders to the Offices of State, That our preſent King is not only <hi>Pater Patriae,</hi> but <hi>Pater Patriarum;</hi> and, like the true Emblem of that Immenſe Diety whoſe Anointed he is, diffuſeth his Favours with a more unconfined and univerſal Influence than any of our late Kings of <hi>Britain;</hi> Their natural Eaſineſs of Temper giving many fatal Opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to the Mercenary Miniſters of thoſe times, both to impoſe on their Maſters, and prey upon the Liberties of their fellow-Subjects: whereas, our preſent King doth not only penetrate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to what is juſt, but hath alſo a Nobleneſs of Soul, to execute, with an impartial Hand, what to him ſeemeth to be ſo. And that the giving his Royal Sanction to this Act, was the effect both of his Juſtice and Gratitude, is plain from the natural Regard which in Reaſon we muſt needs ſuppoſe him to have had to our frank and ſeaſonable Services, when in themſelves they were moſt Valuable, and when indeed he ſtood moſt in need of them.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:137279:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But (you ſay) the Out-cry is, That theſe are ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precedented Conceſſions and Exemptions as never were, or ought to be granted by a Prince to any Society or Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Traders in the World: <hi>Ergo,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hah! Is the Hue and Cry got up then? <hi>I</hi> am glad of it: For certainly, the Great, the Grave, and Wiſe Men of the Nation, do never joyn in that Chorus.</p>
            <p>But to be more ſerious; 'Tis true, that theſe Conceſſions may ſeem ſomewhat ſtrange to a People whoſe Wealth, Capacity, Naval Strength, Forraign Poſſeſſions, Plantations, Forts, and Univerſal Settlements, want no more to carry on what Trade ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they pleaſe, than to will and to execute.</p>
            <p>But on the other hand, if they look upon <hi>Scotland,</hi> and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, as in it ſelf it is, deficient to a degree of Extremity, in all the neceſſary Qualification of Trade above-receited; they muſt owne of courſe, that nothing leſs than theſe Conceſſions and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptions could give this <hi>New Company</hi> a proſpect of ſo much as a Poſſibility of ever grappling with ſuch infinite and almoſt inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perable Difficulties as they (and indeed, all other Beginnings) muſt neceſſarily encounter with: ſo that if ſuch Exemptions had not been granted, we had as good have erected no <hi>Company.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as to theſe Conceſſions being without Precedent, I will not pretend to give an Inſtance of any that are exactly the ſame with the Privileges contained in this <hi>Act:</hi> but if I let you ſee much greater I hope that may ſerve the turn. Nor to do that, need I go ſo far from Home, as to ſearch into the Records of other Nations, ſuch as <hi>France, Holland, Denmark,</hi> &amp; others who have given illimited Powers, &amp; vaſt Encouragements to their reſpective Tradeing Companies; but even in <hi>Scotland,</hi> when we could not be preſumed to have had any great Notions of Trade about Thirty five Years paſt, upon the Reſtauration of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. in his Firſt parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the ſeveral Seſſions thereof, (before the French King
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:137279:6"/>had time to plant his Janizaries in the Court of <hi>England</hi> there were ſeveral Acts pas'd in favours of Trade and Manufactories, with Priviledges and Exemptions far exceeding any in this Act, with reſpect to the Purpoſes for which they were granted, <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis Mutandis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that I may not ſeem to ſpeak altogether without Book I ſhall give you an Inſtance of one for all; namely, the <hi>Act</hi> Paſs'd, in the Year 1661. <hi>For the Fiſhings, and Erecting of Companies for Promoting the ſame;</hi> which being too long to be tranſcribed, I ſend you, by way of <hi>Poſcript,</hi> a ſhort Abſtract of the moſt conſiderable Privileges and Exemptions therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, as they ſtand in order in the Act it ſelf; and all theſe were granted for perpetuity: Whereas all the moſt important Conceſſions in this late Act are limited, ſome to Ten, ſome to Twenty one Years; in which time (God knows) we muſt run very faſt, to come up with any of all our neigbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Nations, who have ſtarted ſo long before Us.</p>
            <p>Now let us further compare both the ſaid Acts, and the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes for which they were ſeverally intended, and then, with reſpect to this laſt, we muſt think of going we know not whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, undergo the Danger of boyſterous Storms, and long Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, with which we are not acquainted: tye up our Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machs to ſtrict, regular, and unaccuſtomed Diets; prepare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Effects of quite contrary Climates, and there pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe Plantations, Collonies, Settelments, and build Forts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet as to the Time when all this will happen, he muſt be a wiſer Men than I, that can tell.</p>
            <p>But as to the former <hi>Act for the Fiſhing,</hi> &amp;c. all Matters thereunto relating were to be tranſacted in view of our own Doors, and in our own Power. But then you'll ask me, How it came to paſs, that this excellent Conſtitution for our Fiſhings has had no better Effect? Why truly, I'll tell you, For the very ſame Reaſon which may poſſibly prove the Overthrow of this New Undertaking (which God forbid) if we have no
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:137279:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>better luck in getting honeſter Men at the Head of it: For the <hi>Dutch,</hi> who have got moſt of their Wealth by Fiſhing in other Mens Waters, looking upon us then with a zealous Eye, found a way (as it was then believ'd) to greaſe a certain Great Man in the Fiſt; who thereupon embarqued himſelf, and all his Friends; with all his Might, on our Bottom; and who being once at the Head of all, thwarted all, over-rul'd all, and ruin'dall: For the Honeſt and Well-meaning Men, finding themſelves no other than Cyphers, grew wearied, and ſo gave up the Cud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</p>
            <p>By all which, you have a plain Demonſtration and Proof, That what may do in one Nation, will not do in another. But I'm reſolved to wait with Patience, and hope for the beſt: <hi>Exitus acta probat;</hi> the meaning of which is in Engliſh, <hi>The Proof of the Pudding is in the eating.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But then (you ſay,) the unanſwerable and thunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Dilemma,</hi> which theſe Grumblers would ſeem, and do actually boaſt, to faſten upon his Majeſty, is That either he muſt retract what he has done, by ſome publick Mark of his Diſcountenancing this <hi>New Company,</hi> or otherwiſe he cannot in reaſon deny the like Conceſſions to the ſeveral Trading Companies of <hi>England,</hi> who have ſo largely contributed towards the Expenſe of this preſent War.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer</hi> This is truly the moſt plauſible Difficulty of all thats offered, and ſuch a Nooſe as may readily catch Larks, but will never gravel the judicious part of Mankind more than any of the former, as being all of one piece. The better to obviate which, <hi>I</hi> ſhall give you a plain, eaſie, juſt and adequat Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel in the like Caſe, As for Example: Suppoſing me Lord of a conſiderable Mannour producing abundance of Corn, Hay, Fruit, and having all the marks of a fertile and well cultivated Soil, which I have Lett to Farm for a certain Annual or Yearly Rent; which Rent I have, by Contract of Marriage, appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:137279:7"/>to the Payment of my Wife's Joynture: in the interim, there comes to me an Under taker, with a Propoſal, That where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as I am alſo Proprietor of a certain piece of unprofitable, waſte Ground, together with ſome Acres of Land quite under Water, both which yield me no Rent; he will engage at his own Hazard, Labour and Expenſe, to cultivate the one, and drain the other, providing I grant him a Leaſe thereof free of all Rent for Twenty one Years, to which I readily and reaſonably aſſent, as foreſeeing the Advantage that muſt thereby accrue, if not to my ſelf immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly, yet to my Heirs and Succeſſors. Upon the executing of which Leaſe, ſhould he who Farm'd my Principal Mannour in manner aforeſaid, come and tax me of being an exacting and partial Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord, if I would not alſo let him ſit Rent-free, as well as his new Neighbour Undertaker, Pray, what Regard do you think I ought to obſerve to any Demand that were grounded only u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon ſuch a Reaſon? The Application whereof is ſo eaſie and natural, that it were calling your Judgment into queſtion, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiate any more upon that Head: Yet leſt you may ſay that <hi>omne ſimile est diſſimile,</hi> and think this to be only an indirect Anſwer to all the Parts of your <hi>Objection,</hi> I ſhall touch them ſeveral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            <p>And, Firſt, As to any publick Mark of His Majeſty's Diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to this <hi>New Company,</hi> which would be the doing and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing of a thing with the ſame breath, is ſo tender a Point, that the very Thoughts of it is attacking and wounding His Majeſty, at once, in two of his moſt peculiar Attributes, <hi>Wiſdom in Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil,</hi> and <hi>Stedfaſtneſs of Reſolution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then as to what Conceſſions may be adviſable to be given to all or any of the Trading Companies of <hi>England,</hi> I muſt ſuſpend my weak Judgment therein, the King, and enſuing Parliament, being the only proper Judges thereof; only thus far I'll venture to judge, That whoever audaciouſly dare pretend to anticipate the Senſe of ſo Great and Auguſt an Aſſembly, by Dictating in Coffee-houſes what his Arrogance thinks, forſooth, they ought
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:137279:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>to do, may likewiſe think himſelf well come off at laſt, if he e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape with only a Reprimand.</p>
            <p>And then as to the laſt Branch of the <hi>Objection,</hi> which ſeems to point at, <hi>our not contributing, ſo largely as they have, towards the Expenſe of the War;</hi> let us conſider, whether they think Us equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerned? and whether We may expect a proportionable ſhare of the Glory and Advantage? If not, then we are but Auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaries, and ought not to undergo any narrow ſcrutiny on that head: For, <hi>A given Horſe ought not to be examin'd in the Mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſuppoſing (as indeed <hi>I</hi> think) We are equally concern'd in the ſame Common Cauſe; it muſt needs be confeſs'd, That we cannot boaſt of any great ſtore of Wealth, (for which we may partly thank thoſe Familiar Spirits of <hi>France,</hi> who by a Leger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demain Trick of <hi>Hocus Pocus,</hi> have too often aſſum'd the ſhapes of Court-Cards, in the moſt conſiderable Games which have (till of late Years) been play'd on the Engliſh Stage;) yet, in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to what our Strength was, in any tolerable meaſure, able to bear, we have always ſignified our good Inclination, by giving ſuch Supplies, from time to time, as have not only rais'd very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Numbers of excellent Troops, but alſo Maintain'd the ſame, till call'd out of the Nation by His Majeſty; &amp; then we ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively rais'd others, to be a conſtant Nurſery for the Engliſh Army. This was all we could do; &amp; could we have done more, we ſtood in need of no Spur to do it: The <hi>Widow's Mite</hi> in the Goſpel was more acceptable to Our Saviour, than all the large Offerings of thoſe who gave only out of the Abundance of their Superfluities: <hi>Of them to whom much hath been given, much ſhal be required.</hi> And if His Majeſty ſhould queſtion us upon this head, we can juſtly anſwer him with a Scripture Phraſe, <hi>Silver and Gold have we none; but ſuch as we have, we give unto him.</hi> True Hearts, and Valiant Hands; Brave Truſty Lads, arm'd with Natural But who dare encounter Fire and Smoke, and whoſe Undaunted
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:137279:8"/>Reſolution and Valour, upon all Occaſions of Trial, have to the Diminution of their Number, given at leaſt ſome ſmall Addition to the Advancing Glory of the Engliſh Arms: which if we had not given, an equal Number of equal Troops from any of our moſt entirely beloved Confederate Princes (if any ſuch they had to ſpare) would certainly be good Meat, but muſt needs have coſt <hi>England</hi> very dear Sauce.</p>
            <p>And ſince I now treat of our Uſefulneſs to <hi>England,</hi> how little ſoever they may value it; I ſhall beg leave to look back again upon the further Motives that induced us to be forward in paſſing this <hi>Act,</hi> and take alſo a further view of the Advantages that may probably ariſe, not only unto our Selves, but to <hi>England</hi> in general, by it.</p>
            <p>As to the Firſt of theſe, we obſerved, That the Cuſtoms, Faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Luxury of other Nations, having bewitch'd our Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Nobility and Gentry, had Introduced a certain kind of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity among us, of uſing &amp; conſuming many more &amp; greater quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities of Foreign Commodities than were ſo much as ever known almoſt to the honeſt Simplicity of our plain &amp; wiſe Fore-Fathers, and more truly than we had ſuperfluous Money to pay for; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially at ſuch exorbitant Rates as are impos'd upon us at the third, fourth, fifth, and (poſſibly) ſixth hand, by our own Ped<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and the exacting Broakers of all other Countries about us. This we ſee a growing Evil, and ſuch as we could not juſtly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for, to our Conſtituents, who were equally concerned, if we had not taken it into our moſt ſerious Conſideration, and with all expedition apply'd the moſt effectual Remedy we could think of; which, after all our Conſultations, and the beſt Advice we could have, terminated in this <hi>Act;</hi> as hoping thereby, that at ſome time or other we may, by degrees, come to have at firſt Hand, and upon an equal Lay, ſuch Foreign Commodities as are now palm'd upon us.</p>
            <p>By all which, you may plainly ſee, we had no ſiniſter Deſign;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:137279:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>we meant no harm to any other Kingdom, State, or Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: <hi>Evil to them that Evil think:</hi> We had no thoughts of drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Neighbours Garden, but of watering our own; and I have no reaſon to doubt, but that the Simplicity and Honeſty of our intention therein, will upon all occaſions meet with a ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Return.</p>
            <p>And as to what further Advantages <hi>England</hi> may probably reap from this <hi>Act;</hi> I think, with ſubmiſſion, that of all ſorts of Men, the <hi>Engliſh East-Indian Company</hi> hath leaſt reaſon to murmur at it; and I am glad to hear the Wiſeſt of them do not, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, any of them (I believe) at their Heart. For, whatſoever Conceſſions, Exemptions, or Eſtabliſhment, the Wiſdom of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Parliament may think fit to grant to that Company, they have reaſon enough, from the conſideration of their own Miſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement, which (I humbly preſume) occaſion'd the late Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſome of them had at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> to ground the beſt part of their Hopes for better Treatment there at this time, upon the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation which Our <hi>Act</hi> hath ſeemingly entitl'd them to raiſe in the Hearts of their Friends in Parliament, whom I heartily wiſh to be many: <hi>Salvo Jure cujuſlibet.</hi> For I am ſure, the World is ſpaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous enough to contain both Them, and the <hi>Scotch Company,</hi> for more Efforts than either one or other, or both of them, are able to put in execution. They may in time, be ſerviceable each to the other, <hi>Manus Manum fricat;</hi> and as I hope, the <hi>Engliſh Company</hi> may have reaſon, before the Determination of the enſuing Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to Thank the King and Parliament. They will at the ſame time be pleas'd to remember, that <hi>they owe us a Day in Harveſt;</hi> that is ſome ſeaſonable piece of Friendſhip.</p>
            <p>Now, if the enſuing Parliament do (as I believe they will) take the <hi>Eaſt-India Company</hi> into their Care, whether out of a particular Regard to the ſaid Company, or with reſpect to the Intereſt of the whole Nation, or out of Emulation, from a mix'd Conſideration of both; I ſhal have infinite Satisfaction,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:137279:9"/>to find that we are ſo far uſeful to our Neighbours, as to let them ſee that to be their Intereſt now, which for ſome Years paſt they at leaſt ſeem'd to have overlooked, till we put them in mind of it. And my Hopes are, That if Emulation will once enter within the Doors of that Noble Aſſembly, they will raiſe their Thoughts upon the very Wings of Emulation, and <hi>take the right Sow by the Lugg;</hi> that is, caſt their Eyes about them, and point at Objects worthy of ſuch Noble Efforts as They only are able to put in Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, by curbing the Enemies of <hi>Britain,</hi> and putting ſome ſtop to the Career and over-grown Greatneſs of its Rivals in Trade: of whoſe Affection or Friendſhip <hi>England</hi> can be no longer ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, than they are ſure of Gaining by <hi>England:</hi> Whereas, We poor Mortals muſt at all times look upon our ſelves as in the State of Matrimony, <hi>For better for worſe:</hi> So if we are not allowed ſome reaſonable meaſure of <hi>Due Benevolence,</hi> that Eſſential Part of Conjugal Duty, the World will certainly look upon Us as the more excuſable, if at ſome time or other we ſhould venture to peep abroad.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But ſtill theſe Grumblers (you ſay) do urge that this <hi>New Company</hi> will Steal vaſt Quantities of Goods both by Sea &amp; Land into <hi>England,</hi> and over-ſtock the Markets there with <hi>Indian</hi> Goods, to be Sold at Under-rates, to the apparent loſs of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> and <hi>Affrican</hi> Companies.</p>
            <p>This is truly a very wide ſuppoſition; yet ſuppoſing it all to be true, (as <hi>I</hi> believe it cannot) pray wherein is <hi>England</hi> hurt by it? For over all <hi>England</hi> there muſt be a vaſt many more Buyers than Sellers of any one particular Commodity, and as <hi>Of two Evils the least is to be choſen;</hi> ſo, <hi>Of two interferring Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, the most publick and univerſal good of theſe two is always preferrable to the other;</hi> then beyond diſpute, the Buyers of ſuch particular Commodity (whom I take to be the Body of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) will find it their Intereſt at all times, to beat down the Market-price, eſpecially of Forraign Goods; otherwiſe our
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:137279:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>Forefathers of both Nations, were very much overſeen to make ſo many Laws, which ſtand yet Unrepealed, againſt the Foreſtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Markets, and the Engroſſing of Commodities into few hands. So that if all Reſtrictions, Limitations, and Prohibitions upon Trade between both Nations were wholly abrogated, the great and natural ends of Trade, would (in my humble opinion) be more univerſally and much better anſwered.</p>
            <p>Now, upon ſumming up the Evidence on both ſides, I find we muſt reckon upon many Enemies beyond Sea: But I hope I may modeſtly conclude, That after a true Scrutiny is made, this Act will meet with no Enemies within the Iſle of <hi>Britain,</hi> but who may be comprehended in one or other of two ſorts, and theſe two (ſome ſay) very near related: The firſt are, ſuch who may ſeemingly grumble at this <hi>Act,</hi> for no other reaſon, but to make a Scaling-ladder of it, to a Wall which (without it) they were paſt all hopes of ever getting over. The others are, a certain ſett of Men, who (like Water-men) row one way, and look another. From both which, I hope, the Legiſlative Power and Government of both Nations will protect this Orphan.</p>
            <p>To conclude then: As Almighty God, in his All-wiſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, often revealeth and brings to paſs his Great and Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Purpoſes, by ordinary and unexpected Means; who knows, but that the harmonious Unity which (I hope) will appear in the Equal, Juſt, and Impartial Management and Adminiſtration of this New <hi>Scotch-Engliſh,</hi> or <hi>Engliſh-Scotch Indian Company,</hi> may, in good time, be a happy Motive and Inducement to (at leaſt) all the Wiſe Men of either Nation, to lay aſide miſplaced Paſſion, the prejudices of Infancy and Education; Reaſon juſtly for their Own and Publick Intereſts ſake; obliterate and bury in oblivion the diſtinguiſhing Names of <hi>Scotch</hi> and <hi>Engliſh;</hi> and then vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily liſt themſelves under the United Banner of Undivided <hi>Britain;</hi> to be one in Intereſt, and Inclination, in Offence and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. From the Conſequences of which happy Day, we may date the <hi>Aera</hi> of <hi>BRITAIN</hi>'s being truly GREAT, And pray,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:137279:10"/>what ſhould hinder it? Nature ſeems to have intended Us for One People, as having concenter'd us within the ſame Liquid Walls; we are the Subjects of One King; we ſpeak the ſame Language, differing only in Dialect, as moſt Counties do; we we profeſs the ſame Religion, differing only in ſome Forms, which may or may not be; our Laws point at the ſame End, to diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute Juſtice, and defend Liberty and Property: All which may be ſoon reconciled, if the Wiſdoms of both Nations ſhould once heartily ſet about it.</p>
            <p>No man alive can have greater Veneration for the Government and People of <hi>England,</hi> or be more tender of giving them any the leaſt umbrage of Offence, than my ſelf: But if any particular perſon will, from the Light within him, apply to his own Breaſt any Expreſſion herein that may ſeem harſh, that's his fault, and not mine: In which caſe, I'd adviſe him, like a Friend, to lie ſtill and be quiet; expiate for any former Eſcapes in his Life, by a better Regulation of his Actions in time to come; ſubmit to all Laws and Ordiances of ſuch as are put in Authority over us, and let the Wiſdom of the Nation rule the Nation.</p>
            <p>If herein I have not anſwered your Expectation, yet you have an inſtance of my hearty and ſincere good Wiſhes to the Intereſt of <hi>Britain,</hi> and of my readineſs to comply with your Deſire, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever you are pleas'd to Command,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>SIR, Your Humble Servant,</hi> PHILONAX VERAX.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>EDINBURGH,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Novem.</hi> 14, 1695.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:137279:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>An <hi>Abstract</hi> of the Priviledges contained in <hi>An Act</hi> (mention'd pag. 7.) <hi>for the Fiſhings,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>SAlt, Cordage, Hemp, Cork, Pitch, Tar, Clapboard, Knapple, Skew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoops and Nets, free of all Cuſtom, or other impoſition whatſoever. All Herring and White Fiſh taken and prepared therewith, free of any manner of Taxation or Burden in the Exportation of the ſame.</p>
            <p>All Strangers concerned therein Naturaliz'd of courſe, and alſo free of all Taxation-upon their other Effects, for the ſpace of ſeven Years next after ſuch their Naturalization.</p>
            <p>All Beer, Ale, Strong waters and other Proviſions for Out-reiking of any Veſsel for the ſaid Fiſhings, free of all manner of Impoſitions whatſoever.</p>
            <p>All Lords, and Proprietors of Land, in all places throughout the Kingdom, where ſuch Fiſhing is carried on, to protect, maintain, and defend the ſame, and all Masters if Ships, Fiſhers, and others what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever thereunto belonging, from all harm and trouble; otherwiſe, to refound and ſatisfie reſpectively all Loſs and Dammage ſuſtained upon their Land.</p>
            <p>All Ships, Boats, and other Veſsels, in the exerciſe of the ſaid Trade of Fiſhing, and their employment therein, no ways Arreſtible by any Creditor: The Fiſhers, Maſters and Servants in the ſaids Veſsels, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the whole time and ſeaſon of ſuch Fiſhing, and their employment therein, free from all Actions of Debt, and no ways convcenable before any Judge or Judicature whatſoever, for any Cauſe or Cauſes Civil, which might be intended againſt them: and generally all the ſaid Perſons, Maſters and Servants, free of all Captions, Arreſtments, or other Attachments on their Perſons, or againſt their Materials and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments of Fiſhing, they being actually ſerving therein allanerly.</p>
            <p>The Stock and Profits thereof free of all Stents and Taxations.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed at <hi>London,</hi> and Re-printed at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> by the Heirs and Succeſſors of <hi>Andrew Anderſon,</hi> Printer to the King's moſt Excellent Majeſty, 1696.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
